software engineering radio episode in 99 transactions.
[Music]
this is software engineering radio, the podcast for professional developers on the web at se - radio dotnet.
se radio prints irrelevant and detailed discussions and interviews on soft engineering topics every ten days.
thanks to our audience and the partners listed on our web site for supporting the hot rod.
[Music]
welcome listeners to a new episode of software engineering radio. in this episode bumped on Onaga are going to discuss transactions.
but before we get started let me remind you that on June 15 there is the deadline for the position papers for your participation.
for the AC radio get-together, so if you want to participate in the get together October 16th and 17th in spire in Germany this year of course.
please make sure you'll send us these position papers small one or two-page papers.
that explain a certain topic that you find interesting that you want to discuss at the gap together.
please make sure this position paper reaches us by June 15.
and by the way please make sure ideally it's either text or PDF and you don't send us Word files or all the FS or something.
okay, thanks, now let's get on with the episode.
as I said it's bumped and are now talking about transactions.
so I don't know what our transactions,
transactions are sort of a all-or-nothing way of dealing with persistent data.
usually the term is used quite loosely, so it can refer to a business transaction as in I give you money you give me a new computer.
but the main focus here will be on on techno transactions as with the database.
I start a transaction do several things and in the end I commit the transaction or I rolled back.
but this technical transaction thing need not need not be about a database.
there are all kinds of other sources of data that can participate in a transaction such as messaging middleware, web services.
um basically any thing that has persistent data or class persistent changes.
so well that's basically what a transaction is, it's about doing modifications treating them as a whole thing one unit of work.
and it has a well-defined beginning what you find end, and all that happens in between is all or nothing.
okay, so when talking about technical transactions we define technical transaction by mainly for properties which.
are atomic, consistent, isolated and durable.
in that context you also maybe know the acronym acid which stands for atomic, consistent, isolated and durable.
so I don't know why don't you start explaining the atomic property?
sure I'll do that, this is sort of the the ideal way of looking at your s transaction.
it's the sort of the beautiful 10,000 foot overflight thing, the way things should be, will get more dirty after that.
um having said that, atomic means the all-or-nothing part of a transaction.
it means while item means cannot be split into several parts.
and it basically means that if several changes to data are made or several persistent modifications are made by the transaction.
they are either all made or none of them is made.
this is very important for for different kinds of systems.
for example let's let's look at a banking system and it will transfer from one account to another.
then to modifications need to be made, this certain amount is deduced from one account and it is added to another account.
and sort of is important for the bank that either both made modifications are made or none of them at all as made.
they are both changed a one-unit, you either want both or none at all, otherwise you are in serious trouble and lose money as a bank.
so that's what the atomic part is about.
um yeah, sort of the the easiest to understand property of the the acid things.
the second of them is consistency, consistent is basically about the idea behind transactions.
so if you want to ensure that things remain consistent it's sort of vague.
and you can't always have this will as you will see presently.
but it's sort of more more a vague vapery kind of thing on the poor transactions that you want to have want to ensure.
but not a well-defined technical thing.
on the third one is isolation,
and this is one of the well sort of the trickiest part of the trickiest property of transactions.
it means this that while one transaction makes modifications the intermediate state is invisible to other transactions running at the same time.
mmm the idea here is that read excess.
well this is basically this is a property that is basically interesting for databases.
the idea here is that read excess is also always part of a transaction which is to some degree isolated from other transactions.
and well let's look at a insurance company as an example.
and there's one person working on a contract for for one of the customers.
and sort of adding things over a long time working interactively with the application.
the transaction running for two or three hours let's say.
well this accountant is or whether this this person is adding data to this insurance contract.
during this time no other person or system in the insurance company must see any of the intermediate states because.
they are plainly inconsistent.
or as an example where this is important is when.
we get back to the banking system with the money transfer between two accounts.
even if the the transfer is atomic it is either it is committed as a whole or rolled back as a whole, you still have intermediate states.
first you do an update statement or well not using update but anyway.
first we modify one of the accounts to deduce the money and afterwards you what if at the second account two to add the money.
and let's say there is a report over all accounts because the bank wants to know how much money it manages actually.
um then this long-running report across all accounts must never see an intermediate state of a transfer from one account to another.
cause then it would either count the amount twice because it was first added to the second account and then deduced from the first.
or not at all because it were first deduced from the other then the report was running then it has added to the second.
that's what isolation is about, you always have or usually have intermediate states that are inconsistent.
and other transactions other systems other users should not see the intermediate states.
always be presented with a consistent um view of the system as a whole.
that's what isolation is about, intermediate states are isolated from from being seen by other transactions.
and the first the fourth property is D durable and means that the the modifications are actually persistent.
a trans transaction is about um about persistent data about persistent state that is viewable perceivable in the long run.
so that's what s it is about, that's what as it stands for.
and those four property are sort of the ideal world view of transactions, the way we would all like to have things but can't always have them.
okay, so as you just mentioned that's the ideal view on on transactions.
however in the real world we have to make some some compromises here, especially with respect to isolation.
so why do we have to make these compromises and what are these compromises?
okay what we just talked about is the the ideal world view of of transactions of isolation, no transactions see anything that happens in between.
um in reality we usually don't have this, and as we will see there are two things to that.
cause there's two reasons why we don't have this or don't want to have it actually.
the first is isolation has a price in terms of processing power and storage space, sort of trade-off between the two.
and the other thing is you you had pay a price in terms of looking.
that is not-- transactions do the same thing at the same time, one has to wait until the other is finished.
that's the the two things that that limit the other, those two things are the price you have to pay for having isolation of having high isolation levels.
to understand this this, let's imagine we want to write a transactional database system,
it's sort of a in mind experiment I like to do in order to understand things.
so let's say we want to implement transactional data modification with ideal isolation.
then there are sort of two naive approaches we could do.
one approach would be that no true transactions takes place at the same time.
so if I have a transaction running and.
you want to try to start a transaction at the same time.
you are blocked until I do a commit on my transaction.
transactions are a lot about concurrency, and this is one easy way to have isolation.
because then of course if you if transaction starts after mine is finished, you will always see a consistent entirely isolated view of the world from my transaction.
this is obviously not a very good approach that because it doesn't scale, it has no concurrency at all.
and for enterprise systems just doesn't work, you want concurrency. so somewhat well.
still naive approaches is just a little bit less naive.
maybe is to copy the entire state of the database at the beginning of every transaction.
sort of as you do with a version control system, you do a branch for each transaction.
do the modifications in the branch and then merge the merge them back when you commit.
this sort of works but it mmm it doesn't have significant overhead in terms of storage.
beginning a new transaction is it would be a very expensive operation copying data or updating internal data structures.
um so this is sort of the the problem the fix you're in if you want to have isolation.
if you want a deal isolation Atem that's expensive.
but for many systems having less ideal relation is fine, the systems don't require absolute isolation.
so for for relational databases the standard describes four levels of transaction isolation we'll look at them presently.
the details of implementations are vendor specific, um and the technology behind them and is the same.
but the names that are used are a little different between the vendors, but well the standard has a standard terminology and you'll find the mapping there.
but the key thing to see here is that you can set the level of isolation separately for every transaction.
so you can have one isolate one transaction with very high isolation because.
this is a really key thing with high concurrency and many transactions are potentially conflict.
and then you have many other transactions with reduced isolation, so you can think about isolation on a per transaction basis.
well let's look at the four levels of isolation that the standard describes.
the first level well in order of increasing isolation would be read uncommitted which is basically no transaction isolation as or at all.
of one transaction modifies data other transactions see the modifications at the same time, this is called a dirty read.
you see modifications intermediate inconsistent modifications done by other transactions.
and this sounds like a very very bad idea, but actually for quite a lot of systems it's okay.
for example if you have web shops on low scale or other small web shops that are mostly read-only databases.
because the product data is stored there all these read transactions on the on the tables that are very rarely updated.
it's perfectly fine to have no transactional isolation there because these transactions don't do any moving modifications that could conflict.
so you can avoid the overhead of having high isolation.
hmm or if you have transactions that work on strictly separate parts of the database, strictly separate rows and your location logic ensures this.
it's perfectly okay to have read uncommitted transaction transaction isolation level.
well but this is no not really isolation, so the next level would be read committed.
which means one transaction sees only those rows in the database that another transaction has acne has already committed.
no updates to existing rows are visible, this means um you have no dirty reads.
the changes become visible only after an update is committed, but there are other limitations.
you still don't have ideal transaction isolation, you have something that's called a non repeatable read.
you read one row with the database in the beginning of a row, your transaction read the same row later on.
and get to something else because another transaction committed it.
let's look at this um from the perspective of the insurance system.
let's say I'm I work on an insurance contract with a long-running transaction.
and you sort of read this do you read the same contract and look at it.
and while you're in one transaction working wizard I commit my changes.
and then while you're still well you are still the same transaction see different values for the UM for the rows that you read at the beginning of your transaction.
for many applications this is perfectly okay to have these kinds of to have this kind of non repeatable read.
but still it is not ideal isolation because.
the something that I committed is visible while your transaction is running.
so you cannot rely on seeing the same state of the database throughout your transaction.
the next level of isolation deals with this arm you have repeatable read.
which means that the database remembers for each row of data that is read by you what the value at the beginning of your transaction was.
and it always returns that even if another transaction commits the data in between.
so if I commit my you my changes to this contract and you do is select on the data well used to select before I do my commit.
and then do to select on the same data after I commit, you still receive the data um you had at the beginning of your transaction.
my changes are not visible although I committed them.
so you have no dirty reads and no non-repeatable reads.
but there's still some limitation to the isolation and that is if I add new rows to the database.
and you do a select statement and return a whole lot of data you my changes become visible.
so with the in the example of the insurance contract, let's say this insurance contract consists of several building blocks that make up the insurance policy.
the insurance policy as a whole, and I add in building blocks in my transaction.
you do a select of with where clause for this contract,
then you receive at the beginning of the transaction just the building blocks that were there before my commit.
if you do the same select afterwards you get the additional building blocks for the policy that I edit.
you you don't get any modifications to the ones you had at the beginning but you get additional rows.
this is what is called a phantom read.
and if you want no phantom reads you want to avoid them you have what is called serializable transaction isolation.
which sort of is the idea that things are the same as if you executed the transactions one after the other.
this is a very very expensive isolation level, it's very expensive to do.
and you don't want to have this for all your transactions.
but for things like well the signing primary keys you often have a table that count that has a counter for assigning new primary keys.
and access to such a table is usually done with serializable isolation.
because there's high concurrency on this table and you already were really really sure that no true transactions modify the table at the same time.
as a matter of fact serializable transactional isolation is not really serializable.
it means that it's mostly as of as if the transactions were done one after the other.
let's not get to a situation where it makes a difference if you do them on after the other adjust with serializable isolation.
um and that is if you read data for the first time you receive that data at the time.
at the commit state of the time when you when you read it.
oh that's somewhat technical, let's go to the time the insurance contract example again.
let's say you read what we are I'm working on the contract and the person have the contract the data.
and you have your transaction and you read the person's personal data should like like a name and address and.
phone number contract data.
then I do my commit or with modifications both through a person and the contracts.
and after that you read the contract for the first time then you receive the contract data after well the version of the contract data after my committed.
because that's the time when you first read it.
so you have the person the personal data of the person in a version before my commit.
and the at the contract data in a version after my commit.
um and for some very paranoid cases this is a problem because it's not really the same as if you did them one after the other.
well one way of doing that if you really want if you really need this.
is um if you have some sort of global things that actually or if you need this you can really see realize things in a physical way.
or um you can address this by story sizing data and have bitemporal databases that kind of thing.
but for the test for the technical support of the database even serializable isolation is not really see realizable.
and well maybe that's enough as for for looking at the dirty details of isolation, I don't want to bore the listeners.
the key thing to remember is isolation is important, isolation is expensive.
and it's important to think what level of isolation do you and how much are you willing to pay for it in terms of concurrency.
so now we had a look in the deep dirty details of isolation, how did the database systems solve the problem internally?
this is a good question and it actually does have some impact on programming so I'll say little about it.
for a read committed that is this is the basic isolation that only committed data is visible.
you have the thing a thing called rollback segments, well most databases do it that way.
that is they as well they sort of do a branch of the data and write modifications of one transaction to a separate part of the of disk.
and have filter all excess of this transaction to the database whenever this transaction reads data it filters it.
merge sort of merges virtually merges the data between the rollback segments and the actual tablespace.
and other transactions access directly access the the main tablespace without seeing this Robeck segment which is sort of a separate part of the disk.
and only when the commit is done the data is actually merged.
so commit is the important is the expensive operation that copies and merges data from the Robeck segment to the to the main table space.
and then checks whether another transaction modified data in the meantime that was modified by this transaction as well.
so if you have concurrent modifications of data the commit fails because the merge of the two versions of data from the Robeck segment of the main tablespace fails.
this is um obviously if.
this obviously solves the problem of isolation.
hmm at the at the row level of edge well you get rid committed isolation but it is an expensive concept.
because if well you sort of copy all the data when you commit it means that you need a bigger rollback segments the bigger your transactions get.
so especially very big transactions become expensive with this Robeck segment approach.
so this sort of the reason why it's a good idea to keep transactions small to keep committed cheap.
and to avoid the the merge conflicts the concurrent modification exceptions.
going beyond the databases use the concept of locks,
that is they mmm one transaction modifies row it acquires a lock that different levels of lock read locks right locks.
are not going to the dirty details here and they are different for different vendors.
but the key thing to remember or to see is um that the database marks different rows as having been read or modified by one transaction.
so if another transaction wants to modify them um it um it is blocked.
mmm and the higher the isolation level the higher the locking level is basically.
for I for serializable isolation ever you if you do it once any if you do is select to one table.
all entries of that table are locked with an update lock sort of like that. the optimizations behind that but that's what it makes it important.
because if you want to have the same result set returned by subsequent selects it means that no other transaction must be permitted to modify the data in the meantime.
so most databases solve these higher isolation levels by serializing XS using locks.
and if one transaction has a lock and another ones to acquire that locks it has to wait until the first transaction is finished.
so higher isolation level reduce concurrency which is the important thing to remember with regard to these locks.
the details as I said our vendor specific, the concepts are little different.
and also the granularity of the locks is different technically well a lot.
no logically it would be a good idea to have locks at the row level.
if you lock one row of a table arm you have a lock only to that.
but there are database systems that.
only lock pages it's usually called pages of data.
that is a group of of because at the granularity which they use to manage their internal spaces.
so you might have surprising reduction of concurrency using these locks.
even if different transactions only access different data there's no overlap at the row level.
you may have overlap at the at the page level because data is at the same on the same page and the page is locked.
the things to remember here it are that.
high isolation reduces concurrency because tape databases lock data lock rows sometimes pages sometimes even who are tables.
and then other transactions wanting to access the same data must wait until the first transaction is finished.
you can have deadlocks if one transaction blocks part a of the database and then wants to access part B.
well the another transaction first locked Part B of the database then wants to access part a.
as with well this is actually a concurrency thing was talked about the concurrency episodes we did.
the thing here is you if you start locking you can have all kinds of deadlocks.
and and breaking of deadlocks by timeouts and that kind of resolution policies.
but locking reduces concurrency by serializing access which reduces throughput and.
is a problem for concurrency is a problem for concurrent access to the database.
again the key thing is keep transactions small and short to avoid these kind of problems.
so i heard that.
for example post press and fire world as well as database implementations use a different approach on locking do you want to say something about that?
yeah I can do that, PostgreSQL for example uses a history based approach.
which it means that every transaction has a global unique number.
and PostgreSQL remembers the global database state through overall tables what the transaction is running and.
returns the the data for one version number while this transaction is running.
and so if other transactions commutator after that is sort of appended to history.
and this gives perfect isolation but it is somewhat experimental still.
and anyway it is it does have performance impacts as well.
so it is a different approach but it's not a solution to all the problems here.
but yes it is a different approach with different trade-offs.
so if you want to go into this and it's about performance you should definitely look at the the manuals of the database systems system you're working with.
all the database systems vary in the way they implement these.
and PostgreSQL has well which optional there as well but it has an alternative approach that has some benefits for significant benefits for some scenarios.
as far as I remember their approach is called my cc which stands for multi-version concurrency control. right, yeah right.
so now we talked about locks on the database level but on the application level we have locks as well.
think about optimistic locking pessimistic locking how do they relate to that?
okay yeah well it's sort of the same term for different things as is so.
often with widely used terms such as transaction.
the problem with locking or the problem these application level locks solve is concurrent modifications of data at the application level.
um let's say we have a web application and it's this insurance application we used to talk about.
and I have one well I open a case I open a contract and work on that.
and you do the same thing at the same time shortly after me.
and then I have my modifications and then I commit them to the database.
and it is it is a web system there mmm the technical the database transaction is closed after the read this not kept open while I'm working in within browser.
so there's one database transaction form for reading the data and presenting it.
and another one for writing the data to the database.
so I write my data to the database and you do the same thing.
you commit your data you write your data to the database in a second transaction overwriting my data without not even noticing that you overrode my data.
last one wins, this is what happens if you have short database transactions but.
long-running um work intervals user interface for example.
so in other words the higher escalation level on database level wouldn't help me here right?
yeah exactly, it wouldn't help you at all because the the database transactions are kept short and small as we well as I suggested.
it's a good idea to have to improve concurrency to have short database transactions.
but then you the database level locking don't doesn't help you to avoid these kind of overwriting conflicts.
you need sort of a higher level solution of the same problem once again.
so on the application level I'm using optimistic or pessimistic locks here right?
those are the two usual approaches that are used actually most of the time.
optimistic locking is the is the better approach, it's sort of if you if you don't want to think about it or don't think about just use optimistic locking.
which basically means there's a counter in every row in the database.
and mmm when.
the when the application writes data to the row it checks that this counter still has the same value as it had when. the data was red.
and then increments it by one.
so in the example I'm when I write my data to the database well well well I read the data from the database.
let's say this counter has the value five for the contract you read the data it's all the contro also has the value five.
and then I commit my data and the the data the application when I successes the database checks that the counter still has a value five which it does.
so it writes my changes and increments the counter.
and then the application wants to write your data it checks if the counter has still has the value five but actually it's incremented to six in the database.
so you get an error message saying that you lose your modifications because someone else modified the data in between.
this is not really ideal especially from your perspective because you use you lose your work.
but at least it's explicit no debt no modifications are lost on the way implicitly.
so you know that someone else did some modifications at the same time maybe you get the information who did it.
if that's part of what is stored in the database so you can call me and we can talk about how it happened.
that we both were working on the same contract the same time.
so there is no implicit loss of data using optimistic locking which.
is often a good idea.
it's it's inexpensive it has no performance overhead at all.
um and in most system the it's a rare case it happens very rarely that people modify the same data at the same time.
so it works quite well in these actually it's quite an interesting util how how you can implement this without having any performance impact.
hmm you can add a check to the where clause of the update statements and then modify the the countable one.
so you have something like update contract set counter to six so counter equals six and all the other fields of the row.
in the where clause you have where counter equals five.
and then the the database driver tells you how many rows were affected and if one row was affected that's great.
because it means on the count room still was five.
but if no row was affected it means that the counter was incremented in the meantime.
so you you know without having any additional sequel statements you need to issue you know that there was an optimistic locking problem.
it's a very very cheap approach and that's the main good thing about it.
so the opposite approach would be pessimistic locking.
which means that I have to explicitly acquire a permission to modify data.
yes exactly, the idea of pessimistic locking is that the application prevents two people modifying the same row.
so if I start working on this contract pessimistic locking would be that there is a flag in the row in the database.
and when I read when I sort of opened the case when I opened the contract this contract would be marked as it is in work.
and the application would prevent any other user from from working on this this contract at the same time.
so we can both open it but you would have a read-only view sort of the same like if you open a Microsoft Word document.
the first person opening this document from a file share arm has can modify it.
and to the second person gets a notification this is a read-only version of the document. um is that okay with you so you still want to open read-only?
that's about this pessimist key locking thing.
whereas persistent persistent data in the database saying this row this contract is in work.
and other application makes sure that no other person can can work on it.
arm this is great for.
really really really preventing to people modifying the same data at the same time.
but it is significant overhead because this it requires application logic to deal with this.
it's hard to to get really right um and take care of all the details.
because you sort of have things like I'm for where applications I open the contract and my browser I close my browser without saving my changes.
and then well the case just remains locked so you need to have some sort of timeout maybe if you that's what you want.
or um you need logic to allow some other person to break the lock.
to say I know this guy's on holiday and he forgot to release the lock before he went on holiday.
so there must be some way to release the lock arm explicitly without having been the one to openly open the contract to have acquired the lock.
you need all kind of logic around it it's very much work to implement.
and the benefit in practice is often very small.
so it's good to know about it but it's not not a very commonly useful thing to do actually.
this is sort of the long-running pessimistic Daxing.
if you have want to have a lock over several technical transactions which is what you usually have in in web applications.
because you don't want to keep check database transactions open for one user over several HTTP requests.
if you can also have some kind of pessimistic locking for for the duration of a single database transaction.
if you have a rich client application you might open it a transaction when the when the data is read.
and then close the transaction is written back again half an hour later.
in that case you can use things like select for update or use these technical locks of the database to implement pessimistic locking.
which reduces the overhead significantly because the database takes care of all these timeouts and inclusive lock release things for you.
so now I know about optimistic and pessimistic locking but when do I use which strategy?
okay well as I said optimistic locking works well if there's it's very unlikely that there's a conflict anyway.
so if most of the time people sort of talk to each other before opening the insurance contracts in their in the application.
it's a rare case that two people are working on the same contract at the same time so there's no problem there optimist locking is look very good for that.
and pessimistic locking is a good choice if you have huge modification.
so it's a really really bad thing if someone loses them as changes because some or other made someone else made a change in the meantime.
or um also part or can also be part of sort of a workflow like thing.
um the contract was hands from one person to another then there's always one person who is responsible for this contract.
and scenarios like that pessimistic locking can be a good idea.
um well the main thing to remember is don't ignore locking.
if you ignore locking just means that the last one to write wins which is usually a bad thing.
and if you're in doubt use optimistic locking.
use pessimistic locking if you see significant benefits for your application for your application logic from pessimistic locking.
okay actually there there's something about the names the names are sort of weird.
they both solve the problem of preventing concurrent modifications.
but the the names are the name stem from from it the attitude behind them.
optimistic locking means well I I want to be really sure that no concur modification occurs.
but I'm sort of optimistic that it's a rare case that two people do the modify has the same data at the same time.
so I'm optimistic that it's a rare thing to happen anyway.
so this is just um well it's just okay to to notify people that one person lost their work but it's a rare thing I'm optimistic about.
and pessimistic means I do these heavy weight precautions because I expect the worst to happen.
and if I'm not I don't well if I'm not really sure no if I don't really ensure that no concurrent modification can occur.
then people will always do the worst.
that's called towards the attitude behind pessimistic locking.
it's like working with version control systems CVS has the optimistic lock approach everyone can modify the same things and commit.
and didn't and CBS tries to merge modifications if two people if I'd the same thing.
and well sometimes you do get a merge conflict but that's okay this is our the optimistic approach.
and the pessimistic approach is sort of explicitly checking out and locking files from version control systems.
others version control systems support this and this is one of the difference between optimistic and pessimistic locking.
yeah clearcase is one example for that right?
yeah well most others I offer both yeah but clique is yes one of those that offer offers locked locks.
so in the first part we talked about database transactions now we talked to plot about application level locks they sort of solve the same problem.
but yeah maybe you can say something about that?
yes sure, um as I said at the beginning transaction the term transaction is used for different things really.
first we talked about the the strict technical transaction concept.
and this these application level locks go more towards the business transaction thing.
and it's a they solve the same problem of preventing concurrent modifications of isolating changes from one another of.
but it's a technical decision with well with valid trade-offs either way how long you want to have your database transactions open for.
call center applications with which clients it's common practice to have dedicated database transactions for each rich client and keep them open all day long.
and that's fine then you can use the pessimistic or look use database mechanisms database transaction mechanisms for locking.
for web applications with high concurrency requirements and indeterminate large numbers of users you want to have very short technical transactions.
and then you sort of add need to add this layer of application level locking on top of them.
okay so basically solve the same problem but with different trade-offs.
because well depending on how long you want to keep your database transactions open.
okay before you said ideally I closed them as soon as possible and keep the transactions as short as possible.
but in some cases as you just mentioned this is not possible which leads us to long-running transactions.
so what do I have to keep in mind when I have to use long-running transactions?
well actually long-running transactions is again one of those things that can mean several things.
long-running transactions can mean as in the example of the call center application that you have technical transactions that are open for long time.
but more often the term long-running transaction refers to long-running logical business transactions.
the the longest one I heard about is the the the process that a new medicine has to go through from its invention until it's approved by the authorities.
this can repeat several years so this is sort of one transaction.
and if it's not if that if this new drug doesn't receive permissions to be used this sort of a rollback logically.
but until it's actually committed and validated it can be several years.
so and you obviously don't want to have a tech new transactions as open for such a long time.
originally the the database transaction was invented to reflect the business transaction and.
worthy but was sort of lean well.
and then sequel sort of was the the users user interface to the application.
um we've gotten a long way since then so we can have long-running transactions but.
cannot be reflected by the technical database transactions at the as well. um obviously if.
you have several technical transactions the debt from the database perspective you.
don't have acid arm properties over this long term.
if they are not atomic for from the database perspective and they're not isolated from the database perspective because you can well other technical sections can see changes there.
so it's absolute application logic to implement this um.
and um one typical approach to this is to implement a state machine.
that one case for example the the drug application or.
the insurance contract application goes through from initial through completely entered into the database.
next state might be proved and next state might be approved by the boss and then actually signed and.
valid something like that.
with different transactions there between these states and.
then it's up to the application logic to deal with this with these states.
and you might for example implement the the isolation by having the applications in one database.
and only when they're finally approved and the contract is signed they're copied into a production database.
and only then they are visible to the booking system that takes care of the financial parts of the contracts.
um or you can have well the simplest case would be that you have a flag.
if the contract is completely complete and signed or still preliminary something like that.
the key point is it's up to the application logic to deal with this um.
and if somewhere along the way one of the step fails this is just a transition in the state machine.
so you for example - the state rejected of the contract.
which means the application the business transaction on the business case or the law in this case.
the business transaction of going we of bring the application to the signing to the signing state arm fails it's rejected.
but it is not a rollback at the database level but rather you have something like an inverse transaction.
you sort of undo the modifications you have made preliminarily.
and then bring the system into a new consistent state with a rejected contract.
it's good to think about um well it's good to think about this and at two levels.
one of them is X of the transactional part you want to complete one thing the whole thing.
and if it fails you undo things you did before.
and the other is to seal to see this sort of as a work slow with with the state machine with transitions between the different states.
and and actions you need to stake to take when you do the transitions.
isolation can be an issue because sometimes it's very important that one user that.
only the user working on the contract can see the details.
if the payment of the person working on the contract um depends on the things he's entering there.
it's important that.
other people co-workers are not able to see this.
so it's it can be an important issue to see to to prevent others from seeing preliminary modifications but that's up to the application logic.
another context in which this concept appears is actually in in long-running workflows.
and this is what what happens off now in service-oriented architectures where.
some different systems cooperate to do to create some some result.
and they're basically you don't even have technical transactions you.
don't have the infrastructure for technical transactions suspending all kinds of different systems.
so one system deals with the application the next one enters data into or when x one checks the consistency against the some back-end system.
the next system notifies some technical infrastructure that's so for for telephone company.
and if this third step fails because some some of the data does not really match or cannot be mapped to the technical infrastructure.
the whole thing must be rolled back.
but you can do a technical rollback so you sort of need to do and in what's called an inverse transaction or compensation transaction.
you sort of a new technicans action you undo the modifications beforehand.
it's the same thing that bank that banking systems do when a transfer fails.
if you do the transfer from one account to another first the money is first a new row is entered to your account history.
saying the money is deduced and it's transferred to this other account.
and then later maybe you gave a wrong account number to transfer to so you transfer fails.
so a new row is added to your arm to new your account balance sheet stating that the transfer failed and the money is again added to your balance.
but those are two different rows it's not a technical rollback of the transfer but it's an inverse or compensation transaction.
this is a good good thing to keep in mind for long-running transactions that spend a longer time or spend more things.
that can be then can be done in a single technical transaction.
so now back to technical transactions so far we looked at transactions with regard to a single stateful server or database.
but what if I have several servers or databases involved?
you're probably talking about distributed transactions two-phase commit is a compliant that kind of thing.
yeah it's sort of popular to have these and it's one of the the buzz words that all application servers need to have.
the idea is if you have several databases participating in your transaction.
um you want to do modifications to one database and to another database or to a database and a messaging infrastructure or local database and web servers or whatever.
um you want to commit the data only if all cysts or you want to have atomicity across several systems.
that's typically the the driver behind it and you want well yeah consistency but atomicity in the term.
of either the changes to both databases are committed or none is committed.
and this yeah consistency is sort of the idea behind it's the vaguest part of acid.
so yeah this was about to keep several databases table several resources consistent to.
sort of merge several local technical transactions into one.
well the naive approach would be if you're finished doing things so you write data to one one of the databases.
write it as the second database commit modifications or the first database commit modifications or the second database.
and often enough this is great it works fine.
but if the second commit fails the second databases says no I don't want to commit this for whatever reason.
you have already committed data the first database and you have lost your atomicity and your consistency across the different systems.
actually there's two different kinds of scenarios against you which you can guard here.
one is that one of the systems participating refuses to commit for well let's say there is a locking issue.
there it notices that it cannot commit because some of the modifications in the conflict with other modifications that were made.
the other is that on some of the processes maybe might be killed.
so let's say you're you committed data the changes the first database and someone then someone killed your process in a hard way.
kill minus 9 on UNIX or something like that.
so that the applicator your process is just gone and you didn't get the chance to to commit modifications the second database.
or someone pulls the network cable before you were able to commit changes to the second database and that way you lose them.
um those are the scenarios that sort of drive the fear towards two-phase commit.
actually there is a standard there it's the ex a protocol for two-phase commit.
and the first prerequisite is that all participating systems support this protocol they are all ex a compliant.
relational debate databases usually do messaging systems often do web services basically never do.
um and um so many many armed mainframe systems don't have two-phase commit support.
so this is the prerequisite in order to be able to have these ex a two-phase commit things all participating systems must support the standard.
the second thing is you need transaction monitor that is you needed some some some process some system that coordinates all the different databases and measures messaging systems.
and all the other systems that.
participate in the distributed transaction on application.
servers often have a transaction monitor ability in arm.
and there are standalone transaction monitors as well.
and if well these prerequisites are present what happens basically is that your application code tells the transaction monitor I want you to commit.
and then the transaction monitor asks all participating system to do a pre comment.
that is to check all prerequisites and have them be really sure that they can commit.
that they that they won't have any objections against committing check all their constraints and everything but do not actually do the commit.
and only if all the participating systems vote yes I want to commit and I'm willing to commit.
only then in a second step that's where the name true phase commit comes from.
in the second step the transaction monitor tells all participating systems to actually do the comet.
and this this guards well against the the second system says oh I can't really commit problem because they're all voted yes I will commit.
but it there's no guarantee that it actually go through in case you pull the network cable at the wrong time.
it actually you can mathematically prove that it's not possible to have any protocol that really really guarantees consistency in all kinds of of evil hardware failure scenarios.
so it's basically a guard against the the the late notification or the to late notification that one system says I cannot commit.
but it's not a perfect guard against hardware failures it's good to keep that in mind.
and actually um two-phase commit is very rarely needed.
the far more common approach is to have some sort of orchestration engine that talks to all the different kinds or the participating systems.
especially in a web service where well this is very widely used but it's useful in other scenarios as well.
so you have one central part that sort of talks to all the others.
and if one of the system says oh I cannot commit then an undue transaction is prim is done and the modifications are are undone.
it's sort of what we talked about in the long-running transaction part.
this often often works very well and two-phase commit as far overrated it's very rarely really useful.
it's very very expensive to have not only in monetary terms but in terms of resource use as well.
so it's good know to know about it when you need it.
but it's often the better approach to think about the compensation transactions you.
can do if some later step fails.
okay I guess that wraps the episode let's do a summary.
okay transactions are an important concept.
um ideally transactions have the acid properties atomic that is all or nothing.
consistent meaning this is what's behind it you want to have consistent data.
isolated meaning while one transaction is running other transactions other people cannot see intermediate states.
and durable the data is actually stored in a persistent way at the end of the transaction.
the long-running transactions especially if you have high isolation are expensive and cause concurrency issues.
because isolation is often implemented using some kind of locking which.
means that um if there's a lot conflict other transactions will have to just wait until one transactions finish.
though the rule of thumb here is we'd use isolation as far as your application can deal with.
and keep transactions short and small in order to avoid the overhead because large transactions tend to be expensive typical database systems.
so four levels of isolation the first one is read uncommitted the next one is recommitted repeatable read and.
finally serializable. yeah exactly.
if you keep your transactions short and small you often read data in one transaction and.
write data another transaction after it's been modified especially in web systems.
and that means that your application needs to take care of ensuring consistency.
optimistic locking is the best approach to to use there because it doesn't add only overhead.
and oftentimes most of the time it's just sufficient.
if you have long-running transactions on the application logic needs to go further and ensure isolation maybe even read isolation.
so that other users may not be able to see intermediate changes.
the data goes through different states as an estate machine with transition transitions between them.
that's up to the application logic to actually deal with these isolation things.
and if you have something like a failure where you would you roll back a technical transaction this means you that you do it compensation transaction or inverse transaction.
sort of adding another modification that undoes the changes the the effect of the changes you don't want to have anymore.
and with regard to two-phase commit and um and x8 Compliance short thing is remember that they are there.
but then forget about it most of the time you don't really need them.
well that about that's about the way I'd summarize what with what we talked about here in transactions.
mmm-hmm okay thanks.
Oh No thank you Ben and thanks everybody for disney bye bye bye.
[Music]
thanks for listening to software engineering radio.
if you want more information about the podcast and all the other episodes visit our website at SE - radio dotnet.
if you want to support us you can donate to the SU radio team by on the website or you can advertise for se radio.
for example by clicking on the dick reddit delicious and /not buttons.
to contact the team lease an email to team @ su radio net.
or if it's specific to an episode please use the comments facility on the website.
so other people can read and.
react to your comments.
this episode of software engineering radio as well as all other episodes are licensed under Creative Commons license.
please see the website for details.
thanks to Charlie crowd and the pot site Music Network for the music used in this show.
the song is called Vegas hard rock shuffle.